http://www.politico.com/story/2013/09/syria-us-russia-chemical-weapons-96472.html?hp=t1_7
	
	U.S. open to Russian chemical weapons proposal - Josh Gerstein - POLITICO.com
	
	The White House says the proposal was no reason for Congress to avoid a vote. | AP PhotoWhite House and State Department officials said Monday they’re open to proposals by Russia to put Syria’s stocks of chemical weapons under international control, but that such talk is no reason for the U.S. to back away from President Barack Obama’s threat of a military strike.The administration’s willingness to consider such a plan offered the first hint at a scenario that might avert a U.S. attack on Syria and could even take the pressure off lawmakers to cast a vote to authorize a military action that his highly unpopular with the war-weary American public.“We’d have to take a hard look. Any transfer of chemical weapons to international control would be a positive development,” Deputy National Security Adviser Ben Rhodes said when asked about the Russian initiative during an interview on MSNBC. “We’ve been highly skeptical to date. They have not even declared their chemical weapons stockpiles.”(Also on POLITICO: W.H.: Russian offer because of U.S. pressure)Rhodes said the U.S. would “follow up” with the Russians on the point “to discuss the seriousness of the proposal,” but he noted that Russia has a record of defending the regime in Damascus.“What we don’t want to have is a stalling exercise where the Syrians don’t follow through on commitments. We’ll take a look at this,” he said.The White House official specifically said the Russian proposal was no reason for Congress to avoid a vote okaying a U.S. military response.“That makes it all the more important we continue to move forward, continue to seek this authorization from Congress and continue to send a message to [Syrian President Bashir] Assad that there will be consequences for his use of chemical weapons.” Rhodes said. “If we don’t do that, you can be certain he will take a green light to continue to use these weapons and certainly won’t be likely to transfer them to international control.”(WATCH: Timeline of Syria crisis response)Former Secretary of State Hillary Clinton, speaking at a previously scheduled White House event on wildlife trafficking, raised the Russian proposal while expressing caution.”Now, if the regime immediately surrendered its stockpiles to international control, as was suggested by Secretary [of State John] Kerry and the Russians, that would be an important step. but this cannot be another excuse for delay or obstruction,” she said, adding that “Russia has to support the international community’s efforts sincerely or be held to account.”Clinton, who said she’d just come from a meeting with Obama, also argued that the Russian offer was a product of the U.S. president’s public declaration of an intent to attack Syria over its alleged use of chemical weapons on its own populace last month.(PHOTOS: What lawmakers said then (Iraq) and now (Syria))“It is very important to note that this discussion that has taken hold today about potential international control over syria’s stockpiles only could take place in the context of a credible military threat by the united states to keep pressure on the syrian government as well as those supporting Syria like Russia,” she said.White House spokesman Jay Carney declined to say whether the president would proceed with an attack even as the U.S. hears out the Russians about their proposal.“You’re spinning forward here. In terms of military action, we’re still engaged with Congress at this point,” Carney said.Rhodes’s comments about a willingness to explore the Russian suggestion were echoed by another White House official who briefed reporters Monday afternoon and by a State Department spokeswoman made similar remarks in what appeared to be a coordinated administration response.(Also on POLITICO: Rice: U.S. inaction in Syria would threaten security)“It’s very important to note that it’s clear that this proposal comes in the context of the threat of U.S. action and the pressure that the president is exerting,” Deputy National Security Adviser Tony Blinken said at the daily White House briefing.Blinken said the proposal did not originate with the U.S. and was not part of an effort by the administration to provide Assad with an opportunity to escape an American strike.“We literally just heard it about this as you did some hours ago,” he said.(Also on POLITICO: John Kerry under fire for 'unbelievably small' comment)Despite the tepid response from the White House, one prominent Democratic lawmaker sounded a positive note Monday about the Russian proposal“I have read the announcement by Russian Foreign Minister Sergey Lavrov that his country has asked Syria to transfer control of its chemical weapons to international monitors for destruction to prevent an international strike. I would welcome such a move,” Senate Intelligence Committee Chairwoman Dianne Feinstein (D-Calif.) said in a statement.“I believe that Russia can be most effective in encouraging the Syrian president to stop any use of chemical weapons and place all his chemical munitions, as well as storage facilities, under United Nations control until they can be destroyed,” she added.U.N. Secretary General Ban Ki-Moon also expressed interest Monday in the Russian proposal and predicted that the international community would act quickly if Syria was willing to turn its chemical weapons over to international control.While Blinken suggested the U.S. was taken by surprise by the Russian offer, the Russians appeared to have seized on comments by Secretary of State John Kerry earlier Monday during a news conference in London.Asked if there is anything Assad could do to avert a military strike, Kerry said: “He could turn over every single bit of his chemical weapons to the international community in the next week. Turn it over, all of it, without delay, and allow a full and total accounting for that. But he isn’t about to do it, and it can’t be done, obviously.”However, White House officials said Kerry was simple reiterating a longstanding U.S. position and not trying to open a new round of negotiations to stave off a U.S. military response to the alleged use of chemical weapons by the Syrian regime on Aug. 21.State Department spokeswoman Marie Harf said the U.S. would welcome the Syrian regime giving up its chemical weapons. “ Clearly, we think that would be a positive step for the Syrian people, for the region, for the whole international community,” she said.However, she said the U.S. was treating the Russian suggestion skeptically because of that country’s record of siding with Assad in his harsh crackdown on opposition forces and civilians.“The Russians for months and years have stood up for the Syrian regime at the United Nations,” Harf said.Please see the Comments FAQ if you have any additional questions or email your thoughts to commentsfeedback@politico.comUpdated: 9/9/13 1:02 PM EDTUpdated: 9/9/13 1:47 PM EDTUpdated: 9/9/13 12:34 PM EDTUpdated: 9/9/13 1:06 PM EDTUpdated: 9/9/13 8:00 AM EDTUpdated: 9/9/13 12:38 PM EDTUpdated: 9/9/13 2:30 PM EDTUpdated: 9/9/13 2:04 PM EDTUpdated: 9/9/13 1:42 PM EDTSkip to navigationSkip to contentSkip to sidebarPOLITICOAboutRSSElectionsElections Home2014 Midterm ElectionsPolling Center2012 Election Results44CongressBlogsDylan ByersCLICKJosh GersteinJoe ScarboroughOpinionPolicyFinanceHealth CareEnergy & EnvironmentDefenseTechnologyTransportation & InfrastructureVideoPhotosEventsPOWERJobsPOLITICO Pro  JOSH GERSTEINContinue ReadingAlso on POLITICO: W.H.: Russian offer because of U.S. pressureWATCH: Timeline of Syria crisis responsePHOTOS: What lawmakers said then (Iraq) and now (Syria)Also on POLITICO: Rice: U.S. inaction in Syria would threaten securityAlso on POLITICO: John Kerry under fire for 'unbelievably small' comment  Back to topJosh Gerstein@joshgersteinWhite HouseRussiaSyriaChemical Weaponshttp://politi.co/1akJEGJComments FAQcommentsfeedback@politico.comcomments powered by Disqus.comments powered by DisqusView More
                            			Play VideoASSAD TO U.S.: 'Expect everything'TIMELINE: Syria crisis responseSunday shows in 90 seconds: All SyriaVANDEHEI:  On Capital New York buySee All Videos »Stories/BlogsVideosPhoto GalleriesTrending NowLast 24 HoursLast 7 DaysPOLITICO publisher buys Capital New York'Unbelievably small'Obama's last best hopeWarren rips SCOTUS as too far rightHistorian remains key ally of rightCharlie Rose interviews Bashar AssadThe party of hawks turns dovish on SyriaWhy Obama's Syria plea won't workThe reality of 'Raising McCain' Hillary Clinton to speak on SyriaPetraeus: Back Obama on SyriaCharlie Rose interviews Bashar AssadObama's last best hope'Unbelievably small'POLITICO publisher buys Capital New YorkWarren rips SCOTUS as too far rightCalendar working against ObamaMcDonough 'outraged' at Cruz's Al Qaeda remarksHistorian remains key ally of rightCuomo blasts BloombergObama could lose big on Syria planPetraeus: Back Obama on SyriaMcCain shames Fox's Brian KilmeadeBiden talks Syria in Situation RoomWallace: Obama in worst possible fixPelosi enforcers wobble on SyriaHouse GOP won't follow their leadersCharlie Rose interviews Bashar AssadWeiner has meltdown with hecklerEpic fall(s) Trending NowLast 24 HoursLast 7 DaysBashar Assad to U.S.: 'Expect everything'Sunday shows in 90 seconds: Syria sell, vote countDenis McDonough: 'Outraged' at Ted Cruz's Al Qaeda commentsSyria: Timeline of crisis responseAnthony Weiner: Mayoral win chances 'good'Sunday shows in 90 seconds: Syria sell, vote countPOLITICO's Turn the Table: Sunday show previewSyria: Timeline of crisis responseDenis McDonough: 'Outraged' at Ted Cruz's Al Qaeda commentsJohn McCain ripped on Syria at town hallPOLITICO's Turn the Table: Sunday show previewPOLITICO Playback: Weiner's mayoral race, Congress debates SyriaPOLITICO's #ThrowbackThursday: Oval Office addressesSyria, Obama & Congress: Latest developments, analysisSecretary Kerry responds to protester of Syria warTrending NowLast 24 HoursLast 7 DaysQUIZ: How well do you know Bill de Blasio?Scenes from SyriaWhat lawmakers said then (Iraq) and now (Syria)Syria:  Where politicians standQUIZ: How well do you know Bashar Assad?Scenes from SyriaQUIZ: How well do you know Bill de Blasio?QUIZ: How well do you know Bashar Assad?Quiz: Do you know U.S.-Syria news?Syria:  Where politicians standSyria:  Where politicians standScenes from SyriaQUIZ: How well do you know Bashar Assad?POLITICO's Cartoon Carousel: The nation's cartoonists' take on the week in politicsObama, world leaders at G-20 summitDylan Byers on MediaYahoo News still committed to newsCLICK The best of last night's late-night T.V.Josh Gerstein on the CourtsMcDonough v. Kerry on SyriaView MoreSee All Drawings »POLITICO HomeElectionsPOLITICO 44CongressOpinionRoger SimonVideoPOLITICO ProEventsDylan ByersCLICKJosh GersteinJoe ScarboroughPlaybookHuddleInfluenceMorning DefenseMorning EducationMorning EnergyMorning MoneyMorning ScoreMorning TaxMorning TechMorning TransportationPro ReportPulseFinanceHealth CareEnergyDefenseTechnologyTransportationAboutAdvertisingArticle ArchiveBookshelfBreaking News AlertsEmploymentFAQFeedbackHeadlinesLog in/RegisterMobile POLITICOPhotosPOWERJobsPressRSS / WidgetsSite MapStaff BiosStoreSubscriptionTerms of ServicePrivacy Policy